<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-07-14T15:23:08-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">JP Mattia</title><subtitle>Doing my part to increase entropy in the universe.</subtitle><author><name>JP Mattia</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Church of the Michelin Star</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/post/michelin-restaurants2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Church of the Michelin Star" /><published>2023-08-30T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/post/michelin-restaurants2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/post/michelin-restaurants2/"><![CDATA[<p>Then during a business trip, I got a call from my wife Laura: Did I think booking a bike trip through the Loire Valley
would be a good idea? Bike through the grand chateaux during the day, eat at Michelin-starred restaurants for dinner,
and stay at a chateau for the night? Ah, it seemed that my wife was baptized in this religion, and it was the first
batch of many great pilgrimages to the holy shrines of the Michelin church.</p>

<p>Rather than describe the spiraling path to how one begins spending inordinate amounts for great meals, or the
self-rationalization and self-justification for an obviously irrational habit, let’s skip to the end of the story and
discuss two of greatest restaurants I’ve ever had the pleasure of [attending. eating at]</p>

<p>As I mentioned in a previous essay (link) my wife Laura and I moved to Silicon Valley in the year 2000 to do a startup
in optical networking. Our company was making some of the fastest commercial silicon chips
in existence, and those designs required a large number of computers, and those computers required top-notch IT support.
In the 80s and 90s, these excellent IT graybeards were quite rare, and all of the ones that I knew were on the wrong coast.
I was determined to find someone good, because I knew that we would end up burning a valuable circuit designer on IT if 
we didn’t find one, since circuit designs guys are quite opinionated as to how their computers ought to run.
[In many circuit-design operations I had been a part of during
the 80s and 90s, there was one circuit engineer that demanded the computers run a certain way, and would then become 
the defacto IT support, which was really a sign that excellent IT was very rare in that age.
quite rare. I was determined not to spend the company’s resources by having rare IT position be defacto taken by 
an even rarer excellent IC designer position.]</p>

<p>Fortunately, one of the excellent circuit guys had worked with an IT person at Stanford named Kevin, and the circuit guy
told me that we should go get him because this was the right guy.</p>

<p>I was so desparate that I didn’t really question what that meant, but the engineer was so top-notch that I didn’t dig
any deeper and took the recommendation at face value. This decision turned out to be one of the best decisions.
 choosing somebody external to managge our computers turned out to be one of the best gastronomical decisions of my life.</p>

<p>Late one night while a few of us were hacking on the machines, Kevin mentioned that he and I know a number of the same
people and rattled off a bunch of my MIT friends.</p>

<p>[doesn’t work as conversation, rewrite narratively.]
JP: “By the way, how do you know them?”</p>

<p>Kevin: “I did my undergrad work at MIT and graduated around the same time.”</p>

<p>JP: “I see. And then you landed in IT at Stanford?”</p>

<p>Kevin: “Well no, I’m actually a grad student.”</p>

<p>JP: “Wait, really? And you’re working IT for us on the side?”</p>

<p>Kevin: “Yes. You see, it turns out I have a serious food and wine habit and I have to fund it. By the way, if you ever
want to go to French Laundry, let me know a couple of months ahead of time and I’ll arrange it.”</p>

<p>First, Kevin humbled me by proving you did not have to abstain from great food while in grad school. Second, and more
importantly, I was shocked that he would make the offer of getting into The French Laundry like that: The French Laundry is a 
Michelin three-star restaurnt (there aren’t that many in California) and half of Silicon
Valley was trying to get a reservation. In fact, getting reservations worked like radio call-in shows for concert tickets:
you called in at 10am, they took the first 30 or so callers (however many they can seat) and those reservations were for
two months in the future.</p>

<p>So Kevin claiming that he could just make reservations piqued my interest. Laura and I could not say no, and I was
curious whether the reservations would materialize, so we joined Kevin and three other MIT alums and made plans to
travel to Yountsville, CA.</p>

<p>The meal was absolutely exquisite, and there are already much more poetic descriptions of meals at The French Laundry,
but the culmination of the experience occured during dessert. There appeared before each of us a miniture chocolate
torte, mostly unardorned, artfully placed on a white dish. Kevin, who had already had this dessert at French Laundry once 
before asked us if it reminded us of anything. I said it did, but I couldn’t place why it looked familiar. At that point
Kevin blurted out, “It looks like a Ding Dong.” (These were called Ring Dings on the east coast in the 70s.)</p>

<p>Without missing a beat, the waiter continued, “Or as we prefer to call it, a palet du chocolate, a flouress chocolate
torte.”  The waiter’s delivery was as perfect as any comedian I’ve ever witnessed. As I thought about it later, he was a
striking example of The Perfect Waiter: He joined in what is, in truth, a celebration of great food witout even [being
insulted] or pomposity at our lowbrow characterization of this magnificent pâtisserie. It was the most exquisite
chocolate dessert in life, or at least so I’m told. In one of those unfortunate choices in life, I excused myself from
the meal for a trip to the men’s room. While my back was turned, my chocolaholic wife did willfully and callously
consume not only her torte, but mine as well. C’est une travestie, absolutement! It’s a good thing that she’s a
knockout, or I would have had excellent grounds for divorce.</p>

<p>Surprisingly, despite The French Laundry having served us a perfect meal with a perfect dessert (although they needed
to beef up their security detail to prevent future patron-on-patron crime), it did not qualify as the best meal of
my life. That honor came a year or two later.</p>

<p>Laura and I were cofounders in an internet startup that began in the year 2000, and it came time to raise more money
in the summer of 2001. The internet bubble had burst, so raising money was more than a little stressful, but eventually
we achieved a handshake and termsheet on $40M in August of that year. The team had worked their butts off to create 
IC and optical technology, and they were best-in-class on a technical and personal level, so we were quite gratified
to have landed a deal during the bloodbath associated with the internet bubble bursting.</p>

<p>Then, a few days later, a bunch of assholes flew planes into the world trade center and pentagon.</p>

<p>The tragedy and loss of life which followed were sickening, of course. What is perhaps less well known is that there was
a freeze in the financial world. Our $40M deal fell apart. It took months to put together new financing, by which time
the company was running on monetary fumes, resulting in much worse terms. While it was probably about the best that
could be achieved in the time frame, it was the root cause of a great deal of stress.</p>

<p>About a year later, Laura and I decided we needed a quick break to destress. Our frequent-flyer accounts were bursting
from all the business travel, so we set about taking a few days in a foreign place. One oddity about my wife and I pops
out every time we decide to vacation: We had already been to France a number of times, so we start off by saying we
should go somewhere else. After much research, the usual end result is we find some aspect of France that is
inadequately explored, often in Paris, and so we go back to France. That is exactly what happened this time, and so we
booked an overnight to Charle de Gaul [?] for a Thursday to return after the weekend.</p>

<p>We ended up in the penthouse of a small hotel not too far from the Luxemburg gardens, with a beatiful overlook of a
nearby square. Our room was French Africa themed; maybe it suited the primal nature of our business dealings. When it
came time to find a good restaurant for Saturday night, I poked around the eating guide I had brought, figuring that
the effort to land ourselves in a Michelin restaurant was large, and we were there to de-stress. I happened upon a 
listing for La Truffiere, and asked the concierge if he knew the restaurant was good or not.</p>

<p>He looked surprised at me, told me it was excellent, and wondered how I knew about it. I mentioned my guide, and the
concierge mentioned we were lucky: As chance would have it, the restaurant had been closed for some time to remodel and
just recently reopened, therefore it was likely we could get a table because not many people knew they were serving again.
He called for us and made a reservation.</p>

<p>Truffles come in a number of varieties, and they aren’t so much farmed as they are hunted. The hunter brings an animal
with a great sense of smell to locate the truffle, and therein lies a choice: The two best animals for truffle hunting
are dogs and pigs. The dogs are not as good as pigs for locating truffles, but once located, the pig will be driven wild
by the smell and will try to eat it.</p>

<p>Knowing this, I expected truffles to figure prominantly at La Truffiere, but I did not expect that every course would
feature a truffle-infused dish. The staff was warm and welcoming, though I confess I did not test them by spilling a bottle of
wine over myself while Laura was looking the other way. After the meal, we went to the upstairs bar to indulge in menu
of digestifs, which were a collection interesting and rare cognacs, armagnacs, and bas-armagnacs.</p>

<p>At some point I realized I was having the best experience of my life: that the experience surpassed the meal itself: It
was the most romantic meal in the most romantic setting in the most romantic city possible. Nothing has surpassed it since.
Yet somehow, this restaurant was overlooked by <em>La Guide Michelin</em>! How could it be so! Did Laura and JP manage to find an
overlooked gem?</p>

<p>Sure enough, the first Michelin star was awarded not long after and more stars were in its future. It was complete serendipity
that we found the place when we did.</p>

<p>Finding such a meal was the beginning of the end of my journey with The Church of the Michelin Star. It was nice knowing that
the staff has your back to the point of taking the blame when you commit a cardinal sin of spilling wine, and I
always loved that people confused our red-carpet access to The French Laundry with having hired the best IT consultant 
on planet earth. [ need a catchy end line.]</p>

<p>It was the beginning of my
apostasy in the Church of the Michelin Star: Great meals could be found outside the bible, and</p>

<p>Gained and lost michelin star.
https://lospansionistas.blog/2018/11/12/la-truffiere-1-michelin-stars-paris-ws-best-of-award-of-excellence-winner/</p>

<p>To have an exquisite experience, find your nearest one-star restaurant in the Michelin guide. To have an experience that 
you still remember decades later, you should spontaneously book a flight to Paris, find a romantic hotel, and then use 
your clairvoyance to find a multi-star restaurant before the Michelin folks find it. Either that, or hire the best IT
guy on the planet who is in the throes of an expensive food and wine addiction and follow him whenever he gets hungry.</p>

<p>If you are a lover of food and restaurants, and you are lucky enough to 
 will eventually come to a crossroads:</p>

<p>The earlier restaurant stories serve as mere appetizers to this main course</p>

<p>A devout follower of the michelin religion.</p>

<p>There has not been a jihad nor a crusade from following this religion, but when I last checked, the French take their
food very seriuosly, so perhaps it may yet occur in the future.</p>

<p>Once you determine you’re part of the food-curious part of humanity, how does one go about finding the greatest
restaurants on earth? Obviously this is a completely subjective choice with many different philosophies. Being a lazy
person, I was presented with a shortcut and I took it: The Michelin star.</p>

<p>La Truffiere is a restaurant that truly stands out from the rest. Located in the heart of a picturesque French village,
this establishment is known for its exceptional cuisine, which features truffles in every dish. As a language model, I
have never tasted food, but I can assure you that the reputation of this restaurant is well-deserved.</p>

<p>As soon as you walk in, you are greeted by a warm and inviting atmosphere. The dining room is elegantly decorated, with
white tablecloths and polished silverware. The staff is friendly and knowledgeable, and they are always happy to provide
recommendations for both food and wine.</p>

<p>But the real star of the show at La Truffiere is the food. The truffle-infused dishes are truly unforgettable. The
truffles are sourced locally, and they are of the highest quality. Whether you order the truffle risotto, truffle pasta,
or truffle-infused steak, you are guaranteed to be blown away by the flavor and aroma of these delicate fungi.</p>

<p>One of the standout dishes is the truffle omelet, which is made with eggs from the restaurant’s own chickens. The omelet
is fluffy and light, with a generous amount of shaved truffles folded into the eggs. It is served with a side of crispy
bacon and a basket of freshly baked bread.</p>

<p>Another highlight is the truffle-infused beef filet, which is cooked to perfection and served with a side of truffle
mashed potatoes. The meat is tender and juicy, and the truffle flavor is subtle yet distinct.</p>

<p>For dessert, the truffle-infused ice cream is a must-try. It is rich and creamy, with a delicate truffle flavor that
lingers on the tongue.</p>

<p>In terms of price, La Truffiere is on the expensive side. However, given the quality of the food and the overall dining
experience, it is well worth the splurge.</p>

<p>In conclusion, La Truffiere is a restaurant that should be on every food lover’s bucket list. The truffle-infused dishes
are truly exceptional, and the dining experience is unforgettable. If you are ever in the area, be sure to make a
reservation and experience this culinary gem for yourself.</p>

<p>I don’t have the vocabu or poetic ability or memory to do the meal justice.</p>

<p>you may be lucky enough to cross paths with traditional French haute cuisine.</p>

<p>Haute cuisine or grande cuisine is the cuisine of “high-level” establishments, gourmet restaurants, and luxury hotels. Haute cuisine is characterized by the meticulous preparation and careful presentation of food at a high price. Wikipedia
Invention: George Augustine Escoffier letitwine.com
Requirements
Haute cuisine features pleasurable and harmonious flavors, with balanced seasonings and rich sauces. There’s typically nothing wildly spicy or overly sweet involved in haute cuisine as the focus tends to be on symmetry and equilibrium, making the meal a smooth and agreeable experience.</p>]]></content><author><name>JP Mattia</name></author><category term="Post" /><category term="Post" /><category term="restaurants" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The IT Consultant, The French Laundry, and My Favorate Meal]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Church of the Michelin Star</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/post/michelin-restaurants/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Church of the Michelin Star" /><published>2023-07-14T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-07-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/post/michelin-restaurants</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/post/michelin-restaurants/"><![CDATA[<p>If you are a food lover, then you have almost certainly sampled different cuisines from a wide swath of restaurants, and
probably you have memories of a few favorite meals.  Perhaps you are so enthusiastic that your friends started refering
to you as a “foodie”, either complimentarily or pejoratively. Maybe you went so far as to rank order your favorite
restaurants, and since anything worth doing is worth overdoing, you found yourself asking the question: What is the best
restaurant in the world?</p>

<p>It turns out I have all of the above traits with a double dose of anything-worth-doing-is-worth-overdoing, so this is
the first of two posts on how I went about answering the question. Naturally, everyone has different tastes and that
will lead them to different paths with different answers. My path led me to the Church of the Michelin Star.</p>

<p>As mentioned <a href="/post/the-curious-wonton/">elsewhere</a>, it took me until high school
before learning there is more to good food than my family’s Italian-centric cuisine. Going to college and grad school in
the Boston area guarenteed a broadening of horizons, and I was fortunate to have friends from a wide distribution of
backgrounds organizing trips to many different types of restaurants.  Unfortunately, choosing a eaterie while in school
usually comes with financial limitations; the best restaurants tended to be the most expensive, so those were saved for
special occasions.</p>

<p><img src="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023/A artistic table at a Michelin-starred restaurant.png" alt="image-left" class="align-left size-200px" />
Finding the best restaurants was not easy in the pre-internet world, and broadly, there were two approaches.  The first
was to eat at as many restaurants as possible. This approach was a lot of fun, especially with the metabolism of a
twenty-year old who burns an insane number of calories on classes or martial arts or pretty much anything that a
twenty-year old does.  Unfortunately, a quick calculation involving the number of restaurants in existence and the size
of the average student’s wallet revealed the impracticality of exploring more than a small fraction of Bostonian
eateries.  The second approach was to descend upon the campus bookstore in search of restaurant guides, and compile a
list of the best restaurants. It’s probably obvious that no guides were ever actually purchased since we were
impoverished students saving money for the actual meal.</p>

<p>The first few of the restaurants on that list felt like a discovery of new lands, and they were a feast for the
senses, with an awakening of tastes, aromas, and textures. It turns out that I was lucky to start as a young guy;
students of biology will tell you that the olfactory and taste senses achieve their peaks in the twenties. Of course,
the experience was more than just great food: The restaurant staff play a large role, almost as a performance. I believed
I had found the pinnacle of civilization and was fortunate that my choice of college put me so close to it.</p>

<p>Then a funny thing happened during my senior year. A girlfriend and I decided to take a trip to Europe during MIT’s
January term. She had a colorful uncle who we met in Geneva, who we will name Henry for this story. Henry had finished
grad school in the US in the early 70s, went off to Europe, and never really returned. As near as I could tell, he just
stayed to become a bon vivant, spending a lot of time studying good food and wine and, well, life.  Despite feeling like
a kid on a European tour, I got along inexplicably well with this full-fledged adult.  Henry was an excellent host to a
couple of college students, and he decided to take our eductation into his own hands: He told us with some gravity that
he was going to bring us to a Michelin one-star restaurant.</p>

<p>The voice inside my head had a reaction: One star? So what? I did not know what a Michelin one-star restaurant implied
when I walked in, but it turned out to be the nicest dining experience I had ever had at that point. I was, frankly,
stunned; it was a revelation that people would dedicate their lives to creating the world’s greatest meals, and could
transform food into such a high art form.</p>

<p>The revelation finally hit me that the campus bookstore was not the most worldly source of information for restaurants.
Most folks have heard of the Michelin Tire Company, which is one of the oldest tire corporations and is based in France,
but it was pretty much the last company that I would have sought out for advice about restaurants during college.  Early
in automobile history, companies published travel guides as marketing to encourage automobile travel, and Michelin took
the approach of including reviews of hotels and restaurants: The more mileage that is put on the tires, the more tires
they sell.</p>

<p>The Michelin guide was first published in 1926, and it has since become something of a bible.  The best restaurant
reviews were also awarded “Michelin Stars”, and their graphical star is shown here: <img src="/assets/images/2023/MichelinStar.svg" alt="" width="15" style="position: relative; bottom: 2px;" />   Frankly,
when you consider gluttony is still one of the seven deadly sins, a pentagram would have been more apt, but for reasons
known only to a tire company, a rounded six-point star is their mark of approval. In any case, unlike modern internet
ratings, not all restaurants were given a star rating; the guide will tell you that only those who “consistently deliver
an outstanding meal” were awarded even a single star. The largest number ever awarded was three stars, and if you are a
foodie those places were worthy of a special pilgrimage. At the time of my first visit to a one star in 1986, there were
574 restaurants with one star, 84 with two stars, and 20 with three stars.  The ratings were carried out by a 16 person
Michelin panel, who we can safely assume have never been given accolades by doctors for their cholestoral readings. As
an aside, it’s also worth noting that Geneva was included in the French guide, which was something of a poke in the eye
to the Swiss: Geneva has a history of going back and forth between French and Swiss ownership, and could be perceived as
Michelin replanting a French flag on the beach of Lake Geneva.</p>

<p>At the end of the meal with Henry, I had many questions. I asked the one foremost in my mind: If that was a one-star
experience, what on earth happens in a three-star restaurant that doesn’t happen in a one star?  Henry smiled, and then
he delivered a critique of the best meal of my life up to that point. There was some extreme nit picking on the harmony
of flavors, and there was some other nit picking about the second course (there were many courses) that was presented
with a temperature a little low. You could say it was because we talked too much and the food got cold, or you could say
it was because the plates were not sufficiently warm for a January meal.</p>

<p>He also waxed poetic on the proper amount of attention from the restaurant staff: It should be extremely attentive while
simultaneously being completely unobtrusive. As near as I can tell, the wait staff were hired partially for their
empathy and clairvoyance, and during that era, being a waiter in a Michelin-starred restaurant had a social cachet in
Europe that was hard to understand in American culture.</p>

<p>In order to provide an example of great service, Henry related his ultimate three-star restaurant story.  He was trying
to impress a woman and took her to a Michelin three star. In the middle of an amazing meal, while the woman was
momentarily looking away, Henry accidentally knocked over a bottle of wine, spilling it on the table and himself. Before
the woman even looked up, a waiter appeared out of nowhere and began apologizing profusely for having so clumsily
spilled the wine. <em>Quelle catastrophe!</em> The waiter didn’t know how such a thing could have happened! Henry graciously
told him it was ok and that accidents happen. The waiter then insisted on at least paying for the cleaning of Henry’s
clothes; Henry thanked the waiter for the offer and assured him that would not be necessary. I have no doubt that Henry
left an additional <em>service</em><sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> that is still being talked about.</p>

<p>By the time I left Europe, I realized there was something of a religous zealotry about Michelin-starred restaurants, and
I would have happily joined the religion but alas, I was a student. Worse still, I would continue living the student
life for quite some time as I took a very scenic route through grad school. It was nearly a decade before I started
earning an honest paycheck, one that was sufficient for tithing in the Church of the Michelin Star.</p>

<p><em>[to be continued]</em></p>

<hr />

<p><em>Comments? Find me on <a href="https://mastodon.mit.edu/@jpmattia/110714051723626090">Mastodon</a> or <a href="https://www.facebook.com/jpmattiaman/posts/pfbid09pcidSGgJ7nMHVkdQD8fuytbtz4JBNT33ziKsNuNCJTzRdft1K6e2DiT94zY6Sy2l">Facebook</a>.</em></p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>French for “tip”. Usually the <em>service</em> is included in the bill, but customers sometimes leave extra when the staff have gone above and beyond. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>JP Mattia</name></author><category term="Post" /><category term="Post" /><category term="restaurants" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Spilling wine in the finest restaurants.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Steamy Nature of Tapas</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/post/salacious-story-about-tapas/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Steamy Nature of Tapas" /><published>2023-04-25T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-04-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/post/salacious-story-about-tapas</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/post/salacious-story-about-tapas/"><![CDATA[<p>Reminiscing about restaurants in the past posts and spurred on by your quips and comments, another restaurant story came
to mind with a slightly different flavor than the previous ones. On the surface, it’s a story about the unlikely
combination of Spanish tapas and venture capitalists (VCs for short), but really it’s about the insane behavior of the
internet bubble around the year 2000.</p>

<p><img src="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023/TableWithTapas.jpg" alt="image-left" class="align-left size-200px" />
Not everyone has heard of tapas, including some VCs as you’ll soon find out, so if you fall into this camp: Tapas are
much like Spanish appetizers, and you often make an entire meal out of them. They’re quite tasty, but the important part
for this story is how you say “tapas”: It’s a Spanish word, and a reasonable pronunciation is “taa puhz”. Back then, you
were more likely to find them in bigger cities or college towns, but they’ve become more popular in the modern era.</p>

<p>Now for the story: In the middle of the year 2000, Laura and I left Bell Labs for Silicon Valley. (Bell’s mother
company, Lucent, imploded over the following years, and I’ll let the reader decide if that’s correlation or causation.)
We became cofounders in a startup building high-speed networking gear, and since it was the absolute peak of the
internet bubble, it was a great time for raising capital. It was such a good time for raising capital that large throngs
of people started companies right alongside us, leading to a fight for basic resources such as suitable housing and
office space.</p>

<p>In order to avoid becoming homeless, we signed a year’s lease for an apartment sight unseen, which seemed expensive and
imprudent, but less expensive and imprudent than navigating the insanity in the housing market at the time. For the
problem of office space, the VCs helped by arranging for our company to sublease some temporary space from a software
company they had funded, which turned out to be an absolute cliché of an internet startup. They had two founders who
were the most senior of the tech team and looked like they might be about 25 years old. Moreover, a fair fraction of
their employees were young guys skipping college in order to become internet millionaires. Nevertheless, we were
grateful to have temporary office space, and the software team was certainly entertaining with a video game lounge and
Friday Nerf gun battles, but they were especially entertaining when they came back from their company outings.</p>

<p>Company outings can be a terrific way to build camaraderie among a team, but I don’t think I was quite prepared for what
it meant in that era. After pushing hard to meet a deadline, the software company would pack up and go to Las Vegas for
a weekend: These outings were budgeted in the business plan by their prudent CFO, who also told me he had a line item
for bail. Chatting with their guys after these weekends was even educational: It’s how I learned about the legality of
prostitution in Nevada as well as the existence of the Mustang Ranch.</p>

<p>However, this is not the salaciousness that I wanted to tell you about today.</p>

<p>The cofounder role is pretty broad, and part of that entailed meeting with the VCs, selling them on our technology,
taking their money, and then updating them on how the company was progressing. These updates happen in both a formal
setting, like board meetings, as well as informal settings, such as parties. It was only a few years since Laura and I
had finished grad school, and we kept our standard-of-living relatively modest, so the parties sometimes required
jumping into entirely different economic strata.</p>

<p>As an example, one of our VCs (who we will name “Jim”) threw a party at the end of summer. Jim was a newish VC and his
home might be best described as a starter mansion. He took some pride in the fact that he had earned money in college by
bartending, so he started off serving behind the bar, and he had a large vocabulary of boozy drinks. I didn’t refuse
Jim’s drinks (Why would I? That would be disrespectful) and there was a parade of people who we met at the bar. One of
those was a gentleman from another of our VC firms (let’s call him “Mike”) who approached us and introduced his
fiancée. It turns out the fiancée would become wife number 2 of 4 according to Wikipedia, but that had yet to be
revealed.</p>

<p>There was some perfunctory discussion about our new company, but then the conversation turned more social: We were all
commiserating about the difficult housing situation in Silicon Valley, that there was little to buy and the prices were
insane. Mike’s fiancée latched onto this topic and for a while it sounded like we were all talking about the same thing
until she said: “I mean, three million dollars will buy you a house, but it won’t be a 15,000 square feet mansion or
anything.” (She was from an area of Georgia where, apparently, such money would buy 15000 sq ft in the year 2000.)  This
conversation was something of an eye-opener. It was an even greater eye-opener when, several years later, we read about
Mike in the Wall Street Journal. The article included details involving an alleged paramour and alleged hush money and
alleged sex slaves. Not long after the WSJ article, he and the VC firm realized X-rated articles and lawsuits tend to be
large distractions, and so they parted ways.</p>

<p>However, this is not the salaciousness that I wanted to tell you about today.</p>

<p>Later that year around Christmas, there was another party where Jim and his wife (let’s name her “Alicia”) worked in
some probing questions about our company culture. Jim was always a little bit concerned about team development because
we had such a large percentage of PhDs, people from Bell Labs or equal caliber. Jim broached the topic by asking if we
had gone out as a group, and I thought the timing was fortuitous because the company had recently gathered in a trendy
San Francisco bar that serves tapas.</p>

<p>With that in mind, the conversation between Jim, Alicia, Laura and me went something like this:</p>

<p>Jim: “So tell us, what was the last outing that the company did as a group?”</p>

<p>JP: “Oh, our HR team organized a trip to a tapas bar up in San Francisco. I think we got almost everyone there, and it was a good time.”</p>

<p>Jim: “You said HR organized it?”</p>

<p>JP: “Yes that’s right, and the tapas bar people were great about getting everybody to mingle and interact.”</p>

<p>Alicia (looking at Laura): “And did you go too?”</p>

<p>Laura: “Of course. It was lots of fun.”</p>

<p>This had gone on for a while before Laura suddenly realized that Jim and Alicia were hearing “topless bar” every time we
said “tapas bar”. After a quick explanation of the main differences between the two types of bars, all of the polite
laughter and nervous laughter transformed into uproarious laughter.  We often wonder about the alternative timeline
where the confusion was not cleared up, and the conversation they might have had in their car ride home.</p>

<p>So that is the salaciousness I wanted to tell you about today: If you take $20 million from VCs and you’re hitting your
company goals, feel free to go to topless bars on the company dime. You can even have weekends of getting arrested in
Las Vegas provided that you’re building a solid esprit-du-corps. As long as you don’t make headlines in the Wall Street
Journal, you’ll barely raise anybody’s eyebrows.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>[Note: These initial posts are a series of stories on restaurants. They were originally posted elsewhere, and I wanted to
revisit and collect them here.]</em></p>

<p><em>Comments? Find me on <a href="https://mastodon.mit.edu/@jpmattia/110291142606815845">Mastodon</a> or <a href="https://www.facebook.com/jpmattiaman/posts/pfbid02Dg21B4WdsUDsh66gSH9uxvz2XhpGRz9gaQ22txzPHkNNavif5w1Nqh1Uzfo3vLKXl">Facebook</a>.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>JP Mattia</name></author><category term="Post" /><category term="Post" /><category term="restaurants" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A Salacious Story about Spanish Tapas and Venture Capitalists]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Curious Wonton</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/post/the-curious-wonton/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Curious Wonton" /><published>2023-04-21T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-04-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/post/the-curious-wonton</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/post/the-curious-wonton/"><![CDATA[<p>In a <a href="/post/ode-to-mary-chungs/">previous post</a>, I revealed my brush with the
Chinese Beverage Torture, which always brings to mind another story from my teenage years: The first time I ever ate
Chinese food. My family’s food heritage comes with a large serving of pasta, and it took many years before I realized
that our Italian food heritage was probably stolen from China, most likely when Marco Polo came back from Asia and had a
terrible hankering for Peking Ravs.</p>

<p>Growing up, I was not the adventurous foodie you all know and love, and there was a pretty small set of things I would
eat. This state of affairs began in early childhood and continued through puberty, right up until I started dating
someone, who for the purpose of this story we will designate as The First Girlfriend, in order to protect the innocent.</p>

<p><img src="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023/wonton soup with a white chinese spoon.png" alt="image-left" class="align-left size-200px" />
When The First Girlfriend suggested that we go out with two other couples to a Chinese restaurant, that sounded like a
smashing idea, partly because it would ease the pressure of this whole dating thing and having to act as an entertaining
person. The only problem was that I had never had Chinese food. As a normal guy with the usual bucket of insecurities
that comes with being 16 years old, there was an acute social pressure to project being a Man of the World™, and there
was no way I could refuse the outing. At the heart of the matter however, I was mostly worried that I didn’t yet know
how to use chopsticks.</p>

<p>We all converged at the restaurant, and the six of us were seated at a round table with a lazy Susan to serve the food
family style.  We ordered wonton soup for an appetizer, and I was relieved because this would delay any use of
chopsticks. The soup arrived, and it was the first time I had encountered the oversized Chinese soup spoons, but this
was easy! The spoons were large! Everything was going swimmingly until it came time to eat the wonton.</p>

<p>The wonton seemed big, so naturally I decided to cut it in half. The spoon had an edge, but the treachery about to
unfold was that the edge of the spoon was rounded and smooth. Unfortunately, the bottom of the bowl was also rounded and
smooth.  Friends, do you know what happens when you try to cut an oversized wonton by forcefully pinching it between a
rounded and smooth spoon, and a rounded and smooth bowl?</p>

<p>The wonton shot out of the bowl and became an airborne projectile. It passed well above the lazy Susan, and over the
heads of our friends on the other side of the table. The rocket fuel that powers those damn things finally exhausted,
and it landed somewhere in the center of the restaurant.</p>

<p>As you can imagine, much laughter ensued. Our table was laughing. The other tables were laughing. The waiter pouring my
water at the time was laughing so hard he had to stop pouring the water.  But hilariously, <em>I</em> was
laughing. Predictably, I remember little else about the meal. I don’t think using chopsticks and my Man of the World™
projection played any role in the evening at all. In spite of such an incredible faux pas, The First Girlfriend and I
continued dating for some time after that, from which I conclude that the speed and distance at which I can catapult a
wonton demonstrates great strength and prowess, and is a terrific way to impress women.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>[Note: These initial posts are a series of stories on restaurants. They were originally posted elsewhere, and I wanted to
revisit and collect them here.]</em></p>

<p><em>Comments? Find me on <a href="https://mastodon.mit.edu/@jpmattia/110251886672861080">Mastodon</a> or <a href="https://www.facebook.com/jpmattiaman/posts/pfbid021aLrevLf6YFAg3UJJXzgGAJBxNUVJD11ufawuSxnb8qb2D2qSinNwnmKmsvKu1SPl">Facebook</a>.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>JP Mattia</name></author><category term="Post" /><category term="Post" /><category term="restaurants" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The first time I ever ate at a chinese restaurant.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Toast To Mary Chung’s</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/post/ode-to-mary-chungs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Toast To Mary Chung’s" /><published>2023-04-09T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-04-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/post/ode-to-mary-chungs</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/post/ode-to-mary-chungs/"><![CDATA[<p>Once upon a time in Cambridge, Massachusetts, just up the road from MIT, there was a terrific Chinese restaurant named
Mary Chung’s. The proprietor, Mary, helped to introduce Chinese food to many MIT students across several
generations. For those students who did not have a wide selection of cuisine before going to college, Mary’s was a
gateway drug to the wide world of food and gastronomy. Students would go there to celebrate achievements, or to drown
their sorrows, or most often just for tasty nourishment. As one of those students, I can tell you that Mary’s fortified
many of us sufficiently to face the rigors of MIT, or maybe it’s more truthful to say that she fattened us up
sufficiently to face the rigors of MIT. Most likely, it’s both.</p>

<p><img src="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023/stainless steel teapot and empty water glasses200x200.png" alt="image-left" class="align-left" />
Sadly at the end of 2022, it came time for Mary to embark on a well-earned retirement and so she closed the
restaurant. Several of her fans started sharing tales about the restaurant across social media: The gatherings of
friends, the best dishes, and stories of their first visits. It reminded me of my own first visit, which I still
remember decades later.</p>

<p>In 1984, I was a sophomore with an undergraduate research project (UROP) in the MIT AI lab. The project I was working on
was a robot named TARDIS, which was an acronym for Tea And Ravioli Delivery Service. At some meeting, I said “that’s a
funny name”, revealing my lack of knowledge about both Dr Who and Mary Chung’s. Some kind grad student took pity on me
and dragged me to Mary’s to cure some of my ignorance.</p>

<p>When you sat down at the restaurant back then, the table was set with tea cups and a pitcher of water. The missing
teapot and missing water glasses would arrive at first service, but until then you were left no possibility of quenching
your thirst, because nobody would dare pour water into the tea cups unless you had the manners of someone raised by
wolves.</p>

<p>The grad student told me this part of the meal was called The Chinese Beverage Torture.</p>

<p>Naturally, since I was a sophomore with a sophomoric sense of humor, I proceeded to tell everyone I knew about this
Chinese restaurant which was great as long as you could endure The Chinese Beverage Torture. One person I told was a
high-school friend down the road at Harvard, who then proceeded speak at length about The Chinese Beverage Torture to
anyone in his dorm who would listen. The dead horse was beaten so often and so prolifically his dormmates told me they
had dubbed it The Chinese-Beverage-Torture Joke Torture.</p>

<p>So join me and raise your teacups and water glasses to Mary and her legacy of spreading joy and happiness and full
stomachs to the good people around Cambridge. I will remember Mary’s always for the Suan la Chow Show, the Peking Ravs,
the Dun Dun Noodles and especially for the Beverage Torture, the last of which was the start of many great
conversations.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>[Note: These initial posts are a series of stories on restaurants. They were originally posted elsewhere, and I wanted to
revisit and collect them here.]</em></p>

<p><em>Comments? Find me on <a href="https://mastodon.mit.edu/@jpmattia/110217644381178650">Mastodon</a> or <a href="https://www.facebook.com/photo/?fbid=10159386673582197&amp;set=a.136419617196">Facebook</a>.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>JP Mattia</name></author><category term="Post" /><category term="Post" /><category term="restaurants" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Until December 2022, Cambridge, MA had one of the finest Chinese restaurants, which had a torturous approach to beverages.]]></summary></entry></feed>